<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: drools | Liquid Sky]]></title>
  <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/blog/categories/drools/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-24T22:26:07+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://kijanowski.eu/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jarosław Kijanowski]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Drools JBoss Rules 5.0 Developer's Guide book review]]></title>
    <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/2009/10/drools-jboss-rules-50-developers-guide.html"/>
    <updated>2009-10-02T17:34:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://kijanowski.eu/2009/10/drools-jboss-rules-50-developers-guide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.packtpub.com/drools-jboss-rules-5-0-developers-guide/book">The Developer&rsquo;s Guide</a> is the second book about
Drools available from <a href="http://www.packtpub.com">Packt</a>. It nicely extends the Drools documentation showing a new point
of view at almost all features.</p>

<p>Although it wasn&rsquo;t always easy to follow I definitely recommend this book to developers who either are starting their
journey with this rule engine or are already familiar with Drools. Examples are not trivial &lsquo;hello world&rsquo; applications.
Especially my favorite Drools Fusion chapter about complex event processing is built up on quite advanced rules for a
fraud detection system.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>One chapter is dedicated to performance, which is a must-read for all who have to deal with a huge amount of rules
and facts. It explains how to write rules to take advantage of node sharing and how to speed up fact propagation
using parallel mode.</p>

<p>Another chapter is dedicated to a complete 3-tier JEE application. It&rsquo;s built up on Hibernate (for persistence),
Bitronix transaction manager (for transactions), Spring MVC (for presentation) and obviously Drools (for business logic).</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s also worth to note is the test driven development style presented in almost all examples.</p>

<p>To sum it up, building rule based services is not an easy task. This book introduces the Drools rule engine and deals
with almost all its capabilities - starting with the core engine functionality, going through decision tables,
complex event processing and business process presentation ending with advanced topics covering performance and
integration points with other systems.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Drools meets Hibernate]]></title>
    <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/2008/07/drools-meets-hibernate.html"/>
    <updated>2008-07-09T19:51:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://kijanowski.eu/2008/07/drools-meets-hibernate</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Drools evaluates facts which are present in the working memory. But it can also reason over data stored in a relational
database. This can be achieved using for example a Hibernate Session to access a relational database and then creating
a query. Objects in the resultset can be reasoned over the same way like facts in the working memory. An article, which
describes this is available in <a href="http://www.kijanowski.eu/index.php?site=articles&amp;article=drools_hibernate&amp;lang=en">English</a>,
<a href="http://www.kijanowski.eu/index.php?site=articles&amp;article=drools_hibernate&amp;lang=de">German</a> and
<a href="http://www.kijanowski.eu/index.php?site=articles&amp;article=drools_hibernate&amp;lang=pl">Polsih</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to the world of rules]]></title>
    <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/2008/06/welcome-to-world-of-rules.html"/>
    <updated>2008-06-23T12:03:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://kijanowski.eu/2008/06/welcome-to-world-of-rules</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever heard about rule engines and thought what it is good for? Have you ever been curious how you could benefit
from using a rule engine in your Java applications? I&rsquo;ve written a short introduction into the world of rules and
characterized a sample implementation called Drools. This article is available in
<a href="http://www.kijanowski.eu/index.php?site=articles&amp;article=introduction&amp;lang=en">English</a>,
<a href="http://www.kijanowski.eu/index.php?site=articles&amp;article=introduction&amp;lang=de">German</a> and
<a href="http://www.kijanowski.eu/index.php?site=articles&amp;article=introduction&amp;lang=pl">Polish</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
