<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: beacon | Liquid Sky]]></title>
  <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/blog/categories/beacon/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-10T22:06:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://kijanowski.eu/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jarosław Kijanowski]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Detecting Qualcomm’s Gimbal beacons in Mac OS X Mavericks and on Android 4.2]]></title>
    <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/2014/02/detecting-qualcomms-gimbal-beacons-in.html"/>
    <updated>2014-02-11T14:52:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://kijanowski.eu/2014/02/detecting-qualcomms-gimbal-beacons-in</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I ordered the <a href="https://www.gimbal.com/">Gimbal proximity beacons</a> and before getting my hands dirty with the iOS and Android SDKs I wanted to smoke test these tiny sweeties.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='/images/2014-02-11-detecting-qualcomms-gimbal-beacons-in/beacon.JPG' width='350' height='350' title='Case, Beacon, Bluetooth V4.0 Dongle'><span class='caption-text'>Case, Beacon, Bluetooth V4.0 Dongle</span></span></p>

<p>How can you detect them and verify they send advertisement packets?</p>

<h2>Mac OS X Mavericks</h2>

<p>First you need a Bluettooth v4 device. I have a <a href="http://www.logilink.eu/showproduct/BT0015.htm">Bluetooth 4.0 Adapter from LogiLink</a>. On my Mac (OS X 10.9.1) in the System Report it shows up under the USB hardware as CSR8510 A10, Vendor Cambridge Silicon Radio Ltd.</p>

<p>So far so good&hellip; Unfortunately under Bluetooth I still had the built-in 2.1 old-timer without LE support. The corresponding LMP version is &ldquo;4&rdquo;.</p>

<p>So how do you get the external device working? Just change the switch behaviour of the bluetooth controller to switch to the internal device as soon as it’s plugged in:</p>

<pre><code>sudo nvram bluetoothHostControllerSwitchBehavior="always"
</code></pre>

<p>Now plug in the dongle and refresh the System Report. The LMP version is now &ldquo;6&rdquo; which corresponds to Bluetooth 4.</p>

<p>Last step to get the Gimbal beacons discovered is to install Bluetooth Explorer. Open Xcode and from the menu choose &ldquo;Open Developer Tool&rdquo; -&gt; &ldquo;More Developer Tools &hellip;&rdquo; which will navigate you to Apple’s download site for developers. Locate &ldquo;Hardware IO Tools for Xcode&rdquo; and install it.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2014-02-11-detecting-qualcomms-gimbal-beacons-in/iotools.png"></p>

<p>Open &ldquo;Bluetooth Explorer&rdquo; and from the menu choose &ldquo;Devices&rdquo; -&gt; &ldquo;Low Energy Devices&rdquo;. Start scanning and if your Gimbal beacons are working properly, you should see tons of advertising messages showing up.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2014-02-11-detecting-qualcomms-gimbal-beacons-in/bluetoothexplorer.png"></p>

<h2>Android</h2>

<p>There’s a free app called <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=me.simplymobile.btsignal">Signal Sniffer</a> which nicely displays your beacon’s activity together with a signal strength.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Two beacons were just fine but the third one was not advertising at all. So I opened up that thing and it turned out that the piece connecting the battery with the circuit board had to be bent a little bit.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
