<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: jboss rules | Liquid Sky]]></title>
  <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/blog/categories/jboss-rules/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-24T22:26:07+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://kijanowski.eu/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jarosław Kijanowski]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using rules to pick up rules - Selectors in Guvnor]]></title>
    <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/2009/07/using-rules-to-pick-up-rules-selectors.html"/>
    <updated>2009-07-24T21:15:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://kijanowski.eu/2009/07/using-rules-to-pick-up-rules-selectors</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When you build a package, all its assets are used to compile it. However you might want only a subset of your rules to
go into a package. Moreover you might want to create different snapshots that include different set of rules.
This <a href="http://kijanowski.eu/index.php?site=articles&amp;article=guvnor_selectors&amp;lang=en">article</a> will show how to use the
Selector feature available in Guvnor to build packages containing only these rules that satisfy user-defined constraints.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[JMS – a new fact provider for Drools via Pipeline]]></title>
    <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/2009/07/jms-new-fact-provider-for-drools-via.html"/>
    <updated>2009-07-08T19:08:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://kijanowski.eu/2009/07/jms-new-fact-provider-for-drools-via</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Drools Pipeline is a great tool that allows to put facts into the rule engine from the outside world. Currently
supported stores are JMS queues and topics and text files. The format of the payload is almost free to choose, since
out of the box you can use JAXB, XStream and the powerful Smooks transformer to convert your data into facts,
which the rule engine is able to consume.</p>

<p>This <a href="http://kijanowski.eu/index.php?site=articles&amp;article=drools_pipeline&amp;lang=en">article</a> explains how to use
Pipelines.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[JBoss Drools Business Rules book review]]></title>
    <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/2009/06/jboss-drools-business-rules-book-review.html"/>
    <updated>2009-06-08T18:35:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://kijanowski.eu/2009/06/jboss-drools-business-rules-book-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s quite difficult to get started with Drools, especially if you don&rsquo;t have experience in developing Java
applications. You might imagine how steep the learning curve is for business analysts, who associates Java with an
island or coffee. However <a href="http://www.packtpub.com/jboss-drools-business-rules/book">this book</a> is aimed at exactly
this group of non-technical people, who have knowledge how business runs, but don&rsquo;t know how or simply don&rsquo;t have the
tools to persist it and &lsquo;transfer it to the world of computers&rsquo;.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Most chapters are kept on a really basic level if it comes to writing Java code. On the other hand it&rsquo;s sufficient to
get started. Moreover all used tools are open source software, which means you can use it for free.</p>

<p>This book goes through almost all parts of Drools, especially the most important for business people like Guvnor,
the application for authoring rules, DSLs allowing to write rules in plain English as well as support for the business
analyst&rsquo;s most favorite tool: Excel spreadsheets.</p>

<p>The author even introduces typical developers&#8217; tools like Eclipse, however I would recommend to go through an updated
guide about installing the Eclipse plugin available in the
<a href="http://downloads.jboss.com/drools/docs/5.0.1.26597.FINAL/drools-introduction/html_single/index.html#d0e1371">Drools docs</a>.
A new requirement, that did not make it into this book, is to set up the Drools rule engine.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a chapter I like very much. It makes very clear that testing rules is an important part of the development cycle
and introduces three different ways to achieve full coverage of all written rules. The inquisitive reader might also
have a look at the QA Analyzer, a quite new and powerful feature available in Guvnor.</p>

<p>One chapter is definitely intended for Java developers - about deploying Drools applications in real world scenarios.
The business people will still be able to follow, since the author keeps things easy and doesn&rsquo;t go to deep into
details, however I would love to read more about this topic.</p>

<p>The last two chapters about rule engine concepts and the newest features are a must-read for all those people who have
read the Drools docs, but still need a different point of view to fully understand how Drools works. This topic is very
important in my opinion, since it lets you write your rules more effectively.</p>

<p>What I didn&rsquo;t like was the use of IE and Excel. Same results could be achieved with open source software, too. But
that&rsquo;s a minor one ;)</p>

<p>All in all, definitely a guide for non technical users, but also for developers, who have given the Drools docs a
(second and third) try and still require a helping hand to sort it out how this Drools thing works and how to use it
properly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Drools5 is out - there's also a book!]]></title>
    <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/2009/05/drools5-is-out-theres-also-book.html"/>
    <updated>2009-05-24T11:54:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://kijanowski.eu/2009/05/drools5-is-out-theres-also-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Drools 5 is available for <a href="http://www.jboss.org/drools/downloads.html">download</a>. The corresponding svn tag is
<a href="http://anonsvn.labs.jboss.com/labs/jbossrules/tags/5.0.1.26597.FINAL/.">http://anonsvn.labs.jboss.com/labs/jbossrules/tags/5.0.1.26597.FINAL/.</a> You can read the announcement on the
<a href="http://blog.athico.com/2009/05/drools-5-released.html">Drools blog</a>.</p>

<p>FWIW, there&rsquo;s also a book available released by Pack Publishing.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>It covers basics, like getting the software, setting up the Eclipse IDE and making your first steps with Guvnor
(a web application for authoring and managing rules) as well as more advanced concepts like support for a domain
specific language, tools for rules testing and the internals of the Drools rule engine.</p>

<p>You can read more about this book on their <a href="http://www.packtpub.com/jboss-drools-business-rules/book">website</a> and
chapter 4, <a href="http://www.packtpub.com/files/jboss-drools-business-rules-sample-chapter-4-guided-rules-with-the-guvnor.pdf">Guided Rules with the Guvnor</a>
is available for free. It&rsquo;s a quick introduction to start with Guvnor. It begins with building a data model in Eclipse,
goes through building a business rule with the guided editor and ends with running a test scenario.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tuning Guvnor]]></title>
    <link href="http://kijanowski.eu/2008/08/tuning-guvnor.html"/>
    <updated>2008-08-18T10:33:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://kijanowski.eu/2008/08/tuning-guvnor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Guvnor is the business rules management system in Drools 5. When you deploy it out of the box, you get an unsecured
web application that stores data in Jackrabbit’s embedded Derby database.</p>

<p>This article explains how to tune Guvnor deployed on JBoss Application Server 4.2.3. It&rsquo;s available in
<a href="http://www.kijanowski.eu/index.php?site=articles&amp;article=tuning_guvnor&amp;lang=en">English</a> and
<a href="http://www.kijanowski.eu/index.php?site=articles&amp;article=tuning_guvnor&amp;lang=de">German</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
